<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The pastor's care and dignity, and the people's duty a sermon preach'd at the assembly of ministers at Taunton, 7th September, 1692 / by G.T.</title>
            <author>Trosse, George, 1631-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63260</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2304</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23764</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07892829</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07892829</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40316</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63260)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40316)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1216:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The pastor's care and dignity, and the people's duty a sermon preach'd at the assembly of ministers at Taunton, 7th September, 1692 / by G.T.</title>
                  <author>Trosse, George, 1631-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 60 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Salusbury and R. Osborne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Clergy --  Office.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40316:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PASTOR's Care and Dignity, AND <hi>The People's Duty.</hi> A SERMON Preach'd at the <hi>Aſſembly of Miniſters,</hi> AT <hi>TA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NTON,</hi> 7th <hi>September,</hi> 1692. By <hi>G. T.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>John Salusbury,</hi> at the Sun in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> and <hi>R. Osborne,</hi> Bookſeller, near the Bear, in <hi>Exon,</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:40316:2"/>
            <pb n="i" facs="tcp:40316:2"/>
            <head>The PREFACE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAD not the unhappy Product of a former Piece pleading for a Seventh-Day Sabbath, a few Months ſince morally neceſſitated; and the Importunity and earnest Intreaties of thoſe whoſe conjunct Deſires were deem'd cogent and undeniable Injunctions, now conſtrain'd, you had never ſeen the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor in print; than whom ſcarce any one more deſires Retiredneſs and Obſcurity, or was reſolved more against appearing in Publick: But as the former Diſcourſe was judged ſeaſonable and proper to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct an Error, ſo this Sermon has been judged (both by others) to be beneficial and uſeful for Practice, eſpecially for the Regulators of others Practice (the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel) unto which if it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce any thing, you ought to thank thoſe
<pb n="ii" facs="tcp:40316:3"/>who have wreſted it from me; for I could not judge it worthy of any better Fate, than other of its Companions, even to breath out its last gaſp in the Pulpit, and to lie buried ever after in ſcatter'd Papers.</p>
            <p>Concerning the Sermon itſelf, I ſhall onely ſay, I have been as exact as well as I could in ſending the ſame Diſcourſe to be printed, that was preach'd, (only a Scripture or two may be added, which were in the Notes, but not deliver'd, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of too great Prolixity, and ſome lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Alteration in a few words.) which if it conduces as much to the Glory of God, and Spiritual Good of Others, (chiefly of my Brethren in the Miniſtry) as I was made to believe by my charitable and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious Auditors, 'twas adapted to, I have all my Deſign, and my Prayer is, that God will make it ſo.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>VALE.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40316:3"/>
            <head>THE Paſtor's Care and Dignity, AND THE PEOPLE's DUTY.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Cor. IV. i.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Let a man ſo account of us, as of the Miniſters of Christ, and Stewards of the Miſteries of GOD.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE holy Apoſtle having in the foregoing Chapter ſharply re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd the <hi>Corinthians</hi> for their factious Adhering to, and Applauding of one Miniſter, or ſome Miniſters, with
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:40316:4"/>the Contempt and Rejection of others, and declaring them to be carnal, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and ſilly in ſo doing, backs his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof, and proves his Charge by ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Arguments:</p>
            <p n="1">1. As that all Miniſters have the ſame Function and Calling, are all La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers with God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That they are all imploy'd in the ſame Work, and carry on the ſame Deſign, the Manuring of God's Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry, the Advancing of God's Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That whatever any Miniſter does of good, whatever ſucceſs he has in his Labours, 'tis not from himſelf, nor from his Labours, nor from his Parts, (his Learning &amp; Eloquence) no nor from yet his Graces; but 'tis alone from God's Bleſſing, and by the Operation of his Spirit. Wherefore the Apoſtle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes with an expreſs Prohibition of this carnal and ſinful Practice.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Let no Man glory in Man, for all are yours: Whether <hi>Paul,</hi> or <hi>Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:40316:4"/>or <hi>Cephas,</hi> all Miniſters; whether Apoſtles, or Evangeliſts, or others, are the Churches for her Edification and Salvation, with all their Abilities, Parts, Graces, and Labours, which are for the Spiritual Good of the People of God; of what Parts or Opinion ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, all thoſe that are found in the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentals of Faith and Practice, that teach what we ought to believe and do that we may pleaſe God here, and be ſaved by him hereafter; tho' they have different Apprehenſions of things at greateſt diſtance from the Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and about the Fringes of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</p>
            <p>And having thus reproved them for and dehorted them from this Over-va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luing of, and Doting upon ſome Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, leſt as 'tis uſual with imprudent and unconſidering Perſons, they ſhould run into the other extream; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they muſt Idolize no Miniſters, they ſhould Conculeat them all; and becauſe they muſt not Over-value any
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40316:5"/>one, they ſhould Undervalue every one of them; he begins this Fourth Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter with the Text, <hi>Let a man ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of us,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>A Man indifferently,<note place="margin">Explication <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> every Man, the higheſt and greateſt, as well as the the loweſt and meaneſt, the moſt learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and unlearned, account, judge, and eſteem; be rationally convinc'd and ſatisfied in his own Mind that we are.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Which primarily and immediately ſignifies Rowers in,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> about, under a M<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter or Patron; and is from thence drawn and uſed to ſignifie other ſorts of inferiour ones in Service, as here Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters or Domeſtick Servants; yet not of the meaneſt or common ſort of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and Servants: But,</p>
            <p>Stewards, Diſpenſators, Diſtributers of Goods from <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>tibua, paſco, rego,</hi> to diſtribute, to feed, to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern; all proper Acts of Stewards: And ſo of the Miniſter's Stewardſhip there is a twofold Stewardſhip, A Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and Domeſtical, the former being
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40316:5"/>the Inſpection and Management of the Eſtate without Doors, Setting and Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, (as we uſe to ſay) Receiving and Diſpoſing of the Revenues, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Such a Steward was he of whom we read in the beginning of the Sixteenth Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter of <hi>Luke,</hi> who behaved himſelf knaviſhly and diſhoneſtly in his Place and Truſt, and left and reſign'd it as knaviſhly as he had kept and manag'd it; for when upon intelligence of his Unfaithfulneſs, his Lord diſcarded him, and required an Account of his Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardſhip, and told him he ſhould be no longer Steward; he goes to his Lord's Debtors, and bids one to abate fifty Meaſures of Oil, another twenty Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of Wheat, which upon their Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count was due to his Lord; that ſo he might have them for his Friends and Harbourers when he was turn'd out; for he was too proud to beg, and too delicate to dig and work: and they that are ſo haughty and nice, when they come to Poverty, are in the Road to Diſhoneſty and Knavery, to get their Livelihood.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:40316:6"/>
            <p n="1">1. Our Lord commends the Unjuſt Steward,<note place="margin">Verſe <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> not for his Injuſtice, but for his Wit, for the Abilities that God gave him, not for the Abuſe that he and the Devil made of them. The other, the Domeſtical Stewardſhip is the Truſt and Charge of the Store and good Things of the Family within Doors, to bring them forth, and to diſtribute them in due time and due manner to the Houſhold, and ſuch an one is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A Servant whom his Lord made Ruler of his Houſhold,<note place="margin">Luke <hi>12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> to give them Meat in due ſeaſon. A Periphraſis and Deſcription of this Steward, as he is expreſly call'd elſewhere.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A Steward whom his Lord ſhall make Ruler over his Houſhold,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> to give them their portion of Meat in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. And this is the Steward here ſpoken of, intruſted with</p>
            <p>The Myſteries of God; the ſecret, ſacred, hidden Things of God, Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, Heavenly, Evangelical Things, My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, and hidden from the greateſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40316:6"/>Schollars, the moſt learned Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers in the World, and from the very natural Man, who cannot diſcern them as they are in themſelves, and according to their own ſpiritual Nature.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Diviſion.</hi> 1. We have here the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Office of Miniſters, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and Stewardſhip; or what they are, Servants and Stewards.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſubject Matter of their Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardſhip, or the Things whereof they are Stewards, <hi>The Myſteries of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Duty of the People, They muſt account them ſo, carry it towards them as ſuch.</p>
            <p>Their Office ſhall be the Doctrine, and the People's Duty part of the Uſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> 1. That Miniſters are Chriſt's Stewards: Tit. 1.7. <hi>A Biſhop</hi> (a Miniſter) <hi>must be blameleſs, as the Steward of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.17. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 1. <hi>A diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> (a Stewardſhip, the ſame word
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40316:7"/>as in the Text,) <hi>of the goſpel is committed unto me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 1.25.</note> So, 2. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Diſpenſation or Stewardſhip which is given to me for you; the Scripture ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly tells us that Miniſters are Stewards, and that their Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Office is a Stewardſhip.</p>
            <p>Which Stewardſhip is no ordinary and common Stewardſhip, but the moſt excellent and glorious, the moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary and uſeful, and the moſt profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and advantageous of all other: Which will appear if we conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whoſe Stewards they are, the Lord Chriſt's and God's, ſo expreſly ſaid to be in the Text. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, that his Stewardſhip was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7.</note> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> by the Lord Jeſus. And they are uſually called in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, the Servants of Chriſt, Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors of God, and of Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> now according to the Excellency and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of the Lord and Maſter, ſo is the Excellency and Worth of the Steward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40316:7"/>Thus a Steward of the King's Houſhold is a far more honourable Perſon, and his Office of greater Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, then any others; wherefore the Miniſterial Stewardſhip muſt be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable more Noble in this ſence then any others.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Over whom, or toward whom they are Stewards, God's Houſe, his Church, the whole Houſhold; autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatively over the whole Church, I mean ſo in a ſafe and well expounded ſence; that is, being once duely or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd and authoriz'd Stewards, they may exerciſe it toward, or over any Society of Men, either without or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Pale of the Church; without in any place of the World, among Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens or Mahometans, where Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence may have caſt them; they have Authority to gather a Church from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them; and if they have Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Opportunity, they muſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour it; and being gather'd, they ought to exert the Office of God's Steward over them. Within the Pale of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40316:8"/>Church, among what Society of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſoever God may bring or place them, or by what Communion of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſoever they may be called, they have there the Authority of Stewards, and if due Conveniency preſent, they ought to exert it alſo: For when a Miniſter for the greater Glory of God, and Profit of the Church, may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from one Society of Chriſtians to another, that Call collates no new Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority on him, but gives him an Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion and Opportunity to exert it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver themſelves. Where-ever a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter comes among Chriſtians (all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things duely concurring,) he hath Authority to exert his Miniſterial Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardſhip over them; ſo 'tis ſaid,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>A Servant whom his Lord hath made Ruler over his Houſhold:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.45.</note> Indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely over his Houſhold, that is, uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally, not over ſome one particular part hereof, or ſome ſorts of Servants therein, but over all. And ſo,</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:40316:8"/>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The Steward whom his Lord hath made Ruler over his Houſhold;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 12.42.</note> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Exception or Limitation. So,</p>
            <p n="3">3. St. <hi>Paul</hi> having ſpoken of Chriſt's Body, which is the Church, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately adds,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 1.24 25.</note> 
               <hi>Whereof I am made a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter according to the diſpenſation of God;</hi> Of the Church, of the Body, not of a particular part of the Church, nor a ſingular Member of the Body, but of the whole in this ſence; not that they can ever ſimultaneouſly exert it over the Church; which is the Anti-chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Uſurpation of <hi>Rome,</hi> who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to be Lord of all the Stewards of God's Houſe, as well as of the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Family: Neither can another e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſucceſſively exert it among all the Congregations of Chriſtians, ſeeing the Univerſal CHURCH is ſo far diſperſt throughout the Face of the whole Earth. So that by their Calling they have ſuch an Univerſal Stewardſhip, though they are in their Imployment limited to particular Parts of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily and Houſhold of God: Now ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40316:9"/>to the Greatneſs and Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Family over which Stewards are placed, is the Worth and Dignity of the Stewardſhip; wherefore ſeeing Miniſters are Stewards over the whole Church of God, ſo vaſtly numerous, and the Family being the moſt glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and excellent for Qualifications and Priviledges, this Stewardſhip muſt in Worth and Excellency ſurpoſs others.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If we conſider the Duration there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, this Stewardſhip is for ever, during Life, being once taken into this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and Office of God and the Church; they are always in it, and are bound while they have Abilities, Opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and any of the Family to officiate over, to diſpenſe to them thoſe Things whereof they are Stewards: For tho' Defects in Nature, and Corporal Inabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, and Perſecutions, and Civil Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments may hinder the Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Miniſtry, they cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive of the Office and Function, but theſe being removed. they muſt be ſure
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40316:9"/>to act as Stewards. Every conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Miniſter has nailed his Ear to the Poſts of the Sanctuary for a perpetual Service;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.16.</note> ſo ſaith St. <hi>Paul, Though I preach the goſpel, I have nothing to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of, for neceſſity is laid upon me: Tea, wo is unto me if I preach not the goſpel, having the ſtewardſhip of the goſpel once committed to him.</hi> A moral Neceſſity was layen upon him to preach it ever after; and if he ſhould wilfully refuſe it, woe would be unto him as a wilful Neglecter of the Duties of his Calling. As conſecrated Prieſts and <hi>Levites</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law never became profane Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but were ſtill accounted Holy to the Lord, and fed and maintained by the holy Things; ſo neither can they, who under the Goſpel are devoted to, and by God taken into this Miniſtry and Stewardſhip, ever alienate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from it; and if they do, they incur the Guilt of horrid Sacriledge: Indeed there may be ſome extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Caſe, wherein it may be lawful for a Man to lay aſide his Miniſterial
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40316:10"/>Function, and aſſume another: As ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe two Brothers, the one a King, the other a Biſhop, (as has been uſual, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the great Riches and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Clergy,) the King dies with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Iſſue, and unleſs the Biſhop, that next Heir to the Crown, ſucceeds, there is a Moral Neceſſity of the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow of Church and State, of the Introduction of Popery and Slave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and the Law of the Land makes the Regal and Epiſcopal Dignities to be utterly inconſiſtent in one Perſon: I doubt not, but 'twould be the Duty of the Biſhop to degrade himſelf, and to lay aſide his Croſier, Miter, and Lawn-ſleeves, and to inveſt the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Robes, and take to himſelf the Crown, the Sword, and the Scepter. But ſuch an extraordinary Caſe falls not out in many Ages. Wherefore ſeeing this Stewardſhip is for Term of Life, it is a more excellent one then thoſe that are but for a few Months and Years, and at the <hi>Bene placitum</hi> of an inconſtant Lord and Maſter.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:40316:10"/>
            <p n="4">4. If we conſider the Subject Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of their Stewardſhip, or the Things they are intruſted with to keep and diſpenſe. In the Text they are called the Myſteries of God; and theſe are.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Word of God, whereof they are the Preſervers and Diſpenſers, the Preachers, the Expounders, and the Appliers: So St. <hi>Paul</hi> in that foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned place tells us,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.16, 17.</note> that a Diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was committed to him, which he calls the Preaching of the Goſpel; and ſo again he tells us,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 1.25</note> That the Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation which was given him, or his Stewardſhip, was to fulfil the Word of God; not to fulfil it in itſelf, for 'tis compleat and perfect in itſelf, and ſo its own end and deſign even the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God in our Salvation: for who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever truly believes the Doctrines, and conſcienciouſly obeys the Commands of our Bible, ſhall certainly be bleſſed of God on Earth, and ſaved by him in Heaven: But the meaning is, to fulfil it as a Miniſter of Chriſt toward them, in a due, full, plain manner revealing,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40316:11"/>preaching, or writing it to them, and preſſing it upon them; and their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion runs thus:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19, 20.</note> 
               <hi>Go and diſciple all nations; teaching them to obſerve all things whatſoever I have commanded you.</hi> And ſo Chriſt ſaid unto them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark</hi> 16.15.</note> 
               <hi>Go ye into all the world, and preach the goſpel to every creature.</hi> The Diſpenſation of the whole Word is committed to them: Of the Promiſes, to declare their Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, their Certainty, and their Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſuitably to apply them. Of the Threats, to ſhew their Dreadful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, their Infallibility, and their Terms, and ſuitably to apply them. Of the Doctrines, to ſhew their Truth, their Harmony, their Natures, their Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency to God's Glory and Man's Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, to expound them, and prove and confute all Errors by them. Of the Commands, to teach their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituality, their Latitude, their Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and to preſs them upon the People for their Obedience and Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:40316:11"/>
            <p n="2">2. The Ordinances and Sacred Rites of Chriſt's Inſtitutions; I mean the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, which are only two, Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm and the LORD's Supper, both which are intruſted to Miniſters, and as Stewards they only have the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of them. So is Baptiſm, <hi>Go and diſciple all nations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19.</note> 
               <hi>baptiſing them in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost.</hi> Thoſe ſame Perſons that are authorized to Teach, are authorized to Baptize, and none other, and therefore we ſay, that if the Form and Matter of Baptiſm be uſed by any prophane Perſon, that is not a Miniſter that is Null, and 'tis no Baptiſm. So is the LORD's Supper; and therefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23</note> 
               <hi>I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of the Lord, that which I alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered unto you, that the Lord Jeſus, the ſame night in which he was betrayed, took bread: and when he had given thanks, he brake it, and ſaid, Take, eat; this is my body, which is broken for you: this do in remembrance of me. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſame manner alſo he took the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40316:12"/>cup, when he had ſupped, ſaying, This cup is the new teſtament in my blood: this do ye, as oft as ye drink it, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of me.</hi> Where he tells us, that he deliver'd to them the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt after the ſame manner that Chriſt inſtituted, as he had received Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty from him. And whoever has a Right as a Steward of God's Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to Adminiſter one Sacrament, has as great a Right and Authority to Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter both.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Diſcipline and Cenſures of the Church are committed to their Diſpenſation, Suſpenſion, Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, Re-admiſſion:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.19.</note> So, <hi>I will give to you the keys of the kingdom of heaven: and whatſoever thou ſhalt bind on earth, ſhall be bound in heaven; and whatſoever thou ſhalt looſe on earth, ſhall be looſed in heaven.</hi> Which is not ſingularly and perſonally appropriated to <hi>Peter,</hi> as the Pope would have it, and ſo to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf his pretended Succeſſors; but was committed to all the Apoſtles, and in them to all Miniſters their Succeſſors
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40316:12"/>in the Miniſtry and Stewardſhip of the Goſpel:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 10.23.</note> 
               <hi>Whoſoever ſins ye remit they are remitted unto them, and whoſoever ſins ye retain they are retained.</hi> From which Paſſages we may gather that Miniſters only have Authority to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude from, and reduce unto, diſcrimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating Ordinancers; though in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular and well-govern'd Churches the People ought to be conſulted with, and the Reaſonableneſs of the Miniſter's Proceedings herein toward any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Member, ought to be evinced, (and this is according to Scripture) and ſo their Approbation required: which ſeems to be taught us in that Paſſage of our Saviour's, in which our Saviour enjoyns, upon the ſtuborn Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitency of a Delinquent,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 1 15, 18.</note> upon a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Addreſs of the wronged Party to him, and upon his taking one or two more with him, that then he ſhould tell it to the Church, and if he refuſed to hear the Church, and for his Obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy be ſentenced by the Church, that then he ſhould count him as a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40316:13"/>and a Publican: Which Sentence of the Church ſeems to be implyed in (as antecedent) the words follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Verily I ſay unto you, Whatſoever ye</hi> (the Church) <hi>ſhall bind on earth, ſhall be bound in heaven, and whatſoever ye ſhall looſe on earth ſhall be looſed in heaven.</hi> And that there ſhould be this Harmony between the Miniſters and the People, and that their Conſent be had in the Cenſures, ſeems to be very expedient, yea, neceſſary to the Ends of Cenſures of Suſpenſion or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication; which are the Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling and Spiritual Profit of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquent, the Warning and the Securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Congregation, the Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Religion, and the Glory of God by all. Now except there be a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence between Paſtor and People, theſe will not be produced for if a Miniſter ſhould deny the Ordinances to a Perſon, and excommunicate him, and yet the People own him as a Brother, he'll little regard his Miniſter's Exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of him, and be apt to be more
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40316:13"/>proud and headſtrong againſt him; the People will be no way ſecured but be in greater Danger to be infected; and by ſuch Diviſions and Animoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Religion will be diſgraced, God diſhonour'd, and the Devil's Intereſt exalted. The like will be if the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould ſeparate from a Member, and the Miniſter own him, the ſame if not worſe Conſequences will iſſue therefrom; wherefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> expre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly enjoyns the Concurrence of the whole Church in Excommunication: Having greatly blamed, and ſharply reproved them for owning the Ince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuous Perſon as a Member of their Society; he commands them, in the Name of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. begin.</note> 
               <hi>When ye are gathered together, and my ſpirit, with the power of our Lord Jeſus Christ, to deliver ſuch a one unto Satan, for the deſtruction of the fleſh, that the ſpirit may be ſaved in the day of the Lord Jeſus.</hi> So he alſo enjoyns them joynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to concur in the Re-admiſſion of that excommunicated Perſon;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2, 8.</note> when
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40316:14"/>he had given ſufficient Evidence of his unfeign'd Repentance, ſufficient to ſuch a Man is this Puniſhment which was inflicted of many, (many, not the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter alone, but with his People,) ſo that contrariwiſe ye (the ſame many) ought to forgive him, and comfort him; leſt perhaps ſuch a one ſhould be ſwallow'd up with overmuch Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row; <hi>Wherefore I beſeech you that you would confirm your love towards him.</hi> Wherefore ſuppoſing that a Miniſter ſhould know a Perſon to be moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of Fellowſhip, and moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of Excommunication; yet if his Crime be ſuch, as he ought not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal, and his People being ignorant of it, and contending for his continuance with them; he may probably ſuſpend his own Act, but 'twould be no way adviſeable to proceed to a formal Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and authoritative Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe ſo more hurt would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to the Church, then good: and Miniſters ought not only not to do thoſe things which are unlawful; but
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40316:14"/>alſo they ought not to do thoſe things which are imprudent and inexpedient: Wherefore ſeeing the things that are committed to Miniſters, are theſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, heavenly, evangelical Things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely more excellent rich and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous then all the Riches, and Mines, and Concerns of this Life, which are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in compariſon of them, therefore their Stewardſhip is more noble and excellent, more uſeful and profitable then any other.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It will alſo appear if we conſider the Ratification of all the Acts of this Stewardſhip by God and Chriſt in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; all that they duely perform in their Stewardſhip, according to God's Word, <hi>Clare non erante,</hi> either in Word or Deed is confirmed by God in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and ſhall be made good for ever and ever. The Threats that they pronounce againſt Sinners and Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites in their Preaching, how preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous or ſecure ſoever they be, ſhall certainly be inflicted by God, (if they perſevere to be ſo;) and all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40316:15"/>and Bleſſings that they proclaim to the Godly and Sincere, what ſad, hard, diſmal, next door to diſpairing Thoughts, they may have of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſhall certainly be made good by God: and ſo whoever they exclude from the Priviledges of the Militant Church here on Earth, ſhall be exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from thoſe of the Triumphant Church in Heaven; according to thoſe Scriptures already quoted, <hi>Whatſoever you ſhall bind on earth, ſhall be bound in heaven, and whatſoever you ſhall looſe on earth ſhall be looſed in heaven: Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſins ye remit, they are remitted; and whoſoever ſins ye retain they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</hi> And thus we have proved that Miniſters are Stewards, and have ſhewn the Excellency of their Steward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and proceed to the Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Information.</hi> It ſerves to inform us,</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the great Uſefulneſs and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitableneſs of the Miniſtry in and to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:40316:15"/>the Church of God; I had almoſt ſaid the Neceſſity thereof thereunto, if it be not abſolutely neceſſary to the <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne-eſſe,</hi> the well-being of the Church: What Confuſion! what Waſte, what Want and Ruine, muſt the Abſence of a Steward cauſe to a great and nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Family, wherein are too many unwiſe and headſtrong Perſons, too many proud and ſelf-conceited ones, too many ſlaviſh and prodigal ones, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> his Abſence would ſoon diſſolve the Houſhold. In the Church of God are too many weak and peeviſh ones, too many proud and ſelf-conceited ones, too many unruly and extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant ones, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who without the Rule and Guidance of a Miniſter, would ſoon diſſolve and ruine Churches. This Metaphor therefore ſhews the Utility and Benefit of Miniſters in the Church of God; as do alſo thoſe others of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Nurſes, Paſtors, Shepherds, Guides, Watchmen, and Embaſſadors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To ſhew that as theſe are uſeful and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to Children, to Flocks, to blind
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40316:16"/>Ones, to Cities, and Armies in time of War, and between diſſenting Nations, ſo uſeful and neceſſary are Miniſters to the Church of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. It informs us in the Error of thoſe who judge Miniſters to be the moſt uſeleſs, contemptible, and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſome Perſons of the Humane Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, and eſpecially if they be plain, powerful Heart-ſearching and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence-ſtartling Miniſters. Theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane and ungodly Wretches are groſly miſtaken, and under dangerous Delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Exhor.</hi> 1. This Stewardſhip of the Miniſters is ſerviceable for Exhortation; and the Object hereof is threefold:</p>
            <p n="1">1. To the Stewards themſelves. 2. To thoſe who intend to be ſo. And, 3. To the Houſhold over whom they are ſo.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To the Miniſters and Stewards themſelves: And here I will only brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly premiſe, that though I am very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and unworthy to adviſe or excite you to thoſe things which you know
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40316:16"/>better, and are more forward to do than myſelf; yet God's Providence, and your Call, bringing me hither, I muſt be your Monitor and Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancer: wherefore I crave your Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Condeſcention toward me, but require your Reverence and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to our ſupream Lord, while I exhort to ſome few particulars: As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That you would ſtill conſider, and walk conſtantly under the due Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of the Greatneſs, the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, the Weight, the Conſequence of this your Function and Stewardſhip; a profound and clear Perſwaſion here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of would be a good, and is a neceſſary Preparatory to what follows.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To be in Abilities, and Qualities, and Practice, and Behaviour what their Function and Stewardſhip require, and exacts from them: To be ſuch, and to act and do as their Office does call for, in all (as much as poſſible) excelling all other Servants to the Family and Houſhold. And here I ſhall take leave to mind you of ſome particulars: As,</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:40316:17"/>
            <p n="1">1. Such muſt be learned (not to mention thoſe Scholaſtical Sciences, which all hold uſeful and neceſſary for underſtanding, analifing, and handling the Word of God, and all others are educated in before they pretend to be Candidates for this Function:) I would here recommend the Eccleſiaſtical Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, and the knowledge of the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Languagues, at leaſt ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent skill in them, if we can't arrive to a critical &amp; exact one. Every Steward ſhould have the Key of his Store-houſe at his own Girdle; if not when his Duty requires his Diſtribution of the Family's Proviſion, he may be to ſeek, or elſe may have a Key with falſe Wards put into his hand: You are wiſe to adapt the Simile. To be able to go immediately to the Fountain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head ourſelves, muſt be more content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſatisfactory, and delightful, then to receive the ſtreams through Pipes, by which we know not what may have been contracted to allay its Purity: And withal, by ſuch a Knowledge we
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:40316:17"/>ſhall be qualified the more eaſily to vindicate the Scripture from falſe Gloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Interpretations which the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned and Heretical are apt to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon it, and more clearly prove the Mind of the Holy Ghoſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Such muſt be ſeen, very well ſeen, in the things themſelves, in the matter of their Stewardſhip, even in all the Myſteries and Oracles of God; they muſt have a clear, diſtinct, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, ſatisfactory Knowledge of all Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinal and Practical Truths; they muſt have a ſpiritual Apprehenſion of them according to their own ſpiritual Nature: How can a Steward ever be a good Steward, and duely diſpenſe thoſe things whereof he has no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge? His Ignorance will make him to miſtake one thing for another, to the diſgrace of his Charge, and to the detriment of the Family:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>The Prieſts lips ſhould keep knowledge, and they ſhould ſeek the law at his mouth: for he is the Meſſenger of the Lord of hoſts.</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:40316:18"/>His Lips, and to be ſure his Head firſt, muſt keep Knowledge, before he can diſtribute it to the enquiring People. So our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Every Scribe which is inſtructed unto the kingdom of heaven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.</note> 
               <hi>is like unto a man that is an houſholder, which bringeth forth out of his treaſures things new and old.</hi> He muſt be ſtored with all due know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the things of God, and have Treaſures of all ſorts of them: which that we may attain, there is required a ſerious, a diligent, a humble, an aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duous and conſtant ſtudying of the Holy Scriptures, with ſervent, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, and conſtant Prayer to God for his Bleſſing our Study in them, and enlightning our Minds, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riching our Souls with them. Which St. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts <hi>Timothy</hi> to,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3, 15.</note> 
               <hi>Till I come, give attendance to reading; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate upon thoſe things, give thy ſelf wholly to them, that they profiting may appear to all.</hi> If ſuch an eminent and enlightned Miniſter as <hi>Timothy</hi> muſt read and meditate to profit himſelf
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40316:18"/>more and more in Divine Knowledge, then much more have we need; and muſt it be our Duty to read and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate daily and conſtantly, that we may increaſe therein: I mean reading in, and meditating on the Word of God, which doubtleſs St. <hi>Paul</hi> chiefly, if not only meant in this his Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to <hi>Timothy,</hi> for he tells him in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother place,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15, 17.</note> 
               <hi>That the ſcriptures were able to make him wiſe unto ſalvation, through faith which is in Christ Jeſus.</hi> All Scripture is given by Inſpiration of God, and is profitable for Doctrine, for Reproof, for Correction, for Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in Righteouſneſs, that the Man of God may be perfect, throughly fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed unto all good Works. So that the Scripture fully and infallibly fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes us with all Truths, with the Confutation of all Errors, with all Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to be preſſed upon all our Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and with a Diſcovery of all Sins to be forbidden: And hereby the Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of God's Myſteries may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly furniſhed for the Diſcharge of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40316:19"/>his Function. And here for the more clear ſatisfactory Diſcovery of the Truths of Scripture, and a more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Uſe and Improvement of them for the Benefit of the Houſhold of God; I would exhort to the framing in our Minds of a Methodical Body of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, of all the Articles of Faith, and of all the Duties of Life. A Steward ſhould keep all his Store and Treaſure in a diſtinct Order, or elſe he may be confounded, when having occaſion on ſome unexpected Emergency, he ſhall be to ſeek and not be able to find what is required he ſhould produce: Such a Method of Theology is called,<note place="margin">Rom. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Analogy of Faith; which we tranſlate Proportion of Faith, wherein every thing is fitly and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably placed, has its proper de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendence one upon another, refers each to other, is proved, illuſtrated, ſtrengthened and confirmed each by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and 'tis called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>;<note place="margin">Tim. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> The Form or the Scheme of the Plat-form of ſound Words, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40316:19"/>ſo in themſelves, efficiently ſo in others; being the grand Inſtrument in the hand of the Spirit to make Souls ſound and healthy in the Faith. Such a Plat-form the Apoſtle would have <hi>Timothy</hi> to hold faſt, to have it always with him; and without queſtion 'tis more noble and uſeful in the Head, then 'tis in a Book: He that hath clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and diſtinctly ſuch a Body of Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in his Head, and has experienced the Grace of God in his Heart, and keeps alive the Graces of the Spirit, will be prepared upon any warning, within a little time, with his Bible (when he can have no other Helps,) only, to preach diſtinctly, orthodoxly, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitably upon any Polemical or Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Point that may be propoſed: by the uſual aſſiſtance of the Spirit of God. Whereas ſuch as decry and jeer at this as Syſtematical Divinity, if they ſhould be engaged to diſcourſe upon ſuch a Subject, and have no opportunity to recur to their own common Places and Collections, nor the help of other
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40316:20"/>Books, would make but ſorrowful, je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>june, conſus'd and blundring work on't.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Such muſt be wiſe and prudent: The former of theſe three you may call Learning or Knowledge; the ſecond you may call Sapience or Wiſdom; and this you may call Prudence and Diſcretion: By which I mean a dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and ſagacious Inquiſition into, and Diſcovery of the Condition and State of the Family, and of each Perſon in it, over which we are ſtated Stewards; that ſo we may know what to diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute of the Myſteries of God unto them, which requires a very careful Inſpection into them and their ways and doings, and a diligent Converſe with them, and Examination of them as far as conveniently we may. A Steward ſhould know the Temper and Conſtitution of the Family, leſt he ſhould give Food where Phyſick is more neceſſary, and ſo hurt inſtead of benefiting thoſe that are committed to his Charge: he ought to obſerve whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they work and deſerve their Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:40316:20"/>or whether they be idle and merit nothing; leſt he ſhould waſte his Maſter's Goods, by giving them to thoſe who ought to have none of them; Miniſters muſt ſo endeavour to know the People of their Charge, as to know to whom they ought to apply the Promiſes; and whom they ought to chear with the Cordials of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and to encourage with all the Priviledges thereof; and to whom they ought to apply the Threats of the Law; and to make them to ſmart with the Corroſives of the Word, and caſt them down by a due Excluſion from Evangelical Communion: who are Babes, and want Inſtruction and gentle Carriage toward them; and who ought to be reproved and ſevere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dealt with: In a word, they ought ſo wiſely and prudently to know their Perſonal Charge, as to know what is every ones due; and ſo to give to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one ſuitably his Proportion and proper Part of the Word, Sacrament, and Cenſures. Which requires great
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:40316:21"/>meaſures of Diſcretion and Prudence: and this is that which is chiefly decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by our Lord Chriſt in thoſe places where he ſaith, that 'tis the part of a wiſe Servant and Steward over God's Houſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.</note> to give them their Meat in due ſeaſon; when 'twill be moſt uſeful for them, and not when 'twould be hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to them.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.</note> And as his Wiſdom is ſhewn in the Seaſonableneſs, ſo alſo in the Quality and Quantity of the Meat which he gives them, which ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to be ſuch as is due to them. Three great Books which a Miniſter ought chiefly to ſtudy, to make him wiſe and prudent, are the Holy Word, his own Heart, and his own People.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Such muſt be ſincere and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; they muſt be Loyal to their Truſt, and according to their due knowledge they muſt diſpenſe what they are entruſted withal. An un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithful Steward may greatly wrong his Maſter, and injure the Family, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by an extravagant Waſting, or a clandeſtine Embezelling of the Goods
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:40316:21"/>committed to him: 'tis therefore an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecial Qualification in a Steward, and eſpecially in a Spiritual and Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Steward, that he be true and truſty: This is the Property our Ssaviour gives of his Servant and Steward,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.45.</note> that he be faithful as well as wiſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 12.42.</note> have an honeſt Heart as well as an able Head, to give his Houſhold their Meat in due ſeaſon. And this the Apoſtle ſpeaks of in the Verſe immediately following the Text.</p>
            <p>Moreover, 'tis required in Stewards,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.</note> that a Man be found faithful, as tho' 'twere the only neceſſary Qualification of ſuch an one. And when he directs <hi>Timothy</hi> to the Properties of thoſe that ſhould be intruſted with the Myſteries of God, he tells him,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>The things that thou hast heard of me among many wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, the ſame commit thou to faithful men, who ſhall be able to teach others alſo.</hi> NOw this Faithfulneſs and Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty to God, excludes all baſe and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter ends of the Stewardſhip, as, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, Riches, Applauſe from Men, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality, Men pleaſing, ſowing Pillows
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:40316:22"/>under Elbows, dawbing with untem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per'd Mortar.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Such muſt be diligent and labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious; Stewards muſt have their heads, their eyes, their hands, their feet buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or they will never diſcharge their Office; Miniſters muſt redeem all the time they can from their Recreations of the Body, from Sleep, from Viſits; they muſt imploy and exhauſt all their ſtrength in this their Stewardſhip; they muſt wear out their Lungs in Praying and Preaching, and blunt their Brains in ſtudying, grudge no Pain nor Labor, devoting their all to, and imploying it in, and laying it out about this their Function:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.</note> So our Ssaviour ſaith, that his Servant muſt be found ſo doing when he cometh; that is, he muſt be always buſie and imployed, very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious and laborious, and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ceaſing; becauſe our Lord's com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is always uncertain. So St. <hi>Paul</hi> commands <hi>Timothy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2.</note> 
               <hi>I charge thee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, and the Lord Jeſus Christ, who ſhall judge the quick and the dead,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:40316:22"/>at his appearing, and his kingdom, Preach the word inſtant in ſeaſon, out of ſeaſon, reprove, rebuke, exhort, with all long ſuffering and doctrine.</hi> Day and night, at all times he muſt labor, when any Conveniency preſented: And he was a moſt excellent Practiſer of his own Precepts; for he tells the <hi>Corinthians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1 15.</note> 
               <hi>That he would very gladly ſpend and be ſpent for them:</hi> Exhauſt his Spirits, Blood, and all for their Souls good. And when he had at <hi>Miletus</hi> called the Biſhops, the Presbyters of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> he tells them in that excellent Speech to them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 20 21, 231.</note> 
               <hi>I kept back nothing that was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable unto you: but have ſhewed you, and have taught you publickly, and from houſe to houſe: All day preaching and praying in publick aſſemblies; and at night inſtructing private families. And again, watch and remember that by the ſpace of three years, I ceaſed not to warn every one night and day with tears.</hi> An excellent Example propoſed for our Imitation.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Such muſt be courageous and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:40316:23"/>magnanimous; Of an undaunted and fearleſs Spirit in the Diſcharge of their Office. Stewards muſt be ſo, or elſe every ſawcy and unruly Fellow will daunt them, and tread them down, and ſo either make them ceaſe to Diſcharge their Duty, or elſe out of fear to act quite contrary thereto. So muſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, becauſe they will meet with Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts, Accuſations, Contradictions, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Intreaties from ſome other of the Family; beſides Perſecutions of all ſorts from abroad, (if the Devil can raiſe them) even all Perſecutions of Tongue, Hands, Sword, Priſons, Gibbets, and Flames; and the more able, wiſe, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and laborious they are, the greater Oppoſitions, and more ſtout and dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Encounters they are likely to meet with, even in the Church are Tares as well as Wheat, Chaff as well as good Grain, bad as well as good Fiſh, Veſſels of Wood and Earth, and to Diſhonour, as well as Veſſels of Gold and Silver, and tho Honour; and from theſe, if for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Perſecutions come not, they muſt
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:40316:23"/>expect, and will experience, very great Oppoſitions and Diſcouragements, and therefore they muſt have a courage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Spirit, and a Countenance like a Wall of Iron, and a Gate of Braſs; or they will never be able to bear up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, and wade thro' all theſe: God therefore forbids his Prophets this car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Fear of Men, as,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>Gird up thy loins and ariſe, and ſpeak unto them all that I command thee: Be not diſmayed at their faces, lest I confound thee before them.</hi> So alſo, <hi>Son of man, be not afraid of them, neither be afraid of their words,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 2.6.</note> 
               <hi>tho' briars and thorns be with thee, and thou dost dwell among ſcorpions: be not afraid of their words, nor be diſmayed at their looks, though they be a rebellious houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. Such muſt be zealous for God's Glory, and devoted to his Honour: Stewards muſt be heartily affected with, and ſwayed by their Maſter's In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, and muſt look upon their Lord's Reputation as their own grand Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern; and this will engage them to be
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:40316:24"/>prudent, faithful, diligent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in their Place. So muſt Miniſters be toward <hi>God,</hi> toward his Name, Kingdom, and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. So was St. <hi>Paul</hi> that glorious Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, that incomparable Example of all Stewards; who did and ſuffered more for the Glory of his Lord, and for the Good of his Houſhold, then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.20.</note> he tells us, <hi>That 'twas his earnest expectation, and his hope, that in nothing he ſhould be aſhamed; but that with all boldneſs, as always, ſo then alſo, Christ ſhould be magnified in his body, whether 'twere by life or by death.</hi> He would labor, he would ſuffer, he would live induſtriouſly, and wear out him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; he would dieſhamefully, and give up himſelf for the Magnification of the Lord Jeſus. And ſo in other places he profeſſes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 20.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bonds and afflictions abide me, neither count I my life dear unto myſelf, ſo I might finiſh my courſe with joy; and the miniſtry which I have received of the Lord Jeſus, to teſtifie the goſpel of the grace of God.</hi> So that he might teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Goſpel, and introduce <hi>Jews</hi> and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:40316:24"/>
               <hi>Gentiles</hi> to believe in Chriſt, and to worſhip God, he would willingly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo all Perſecutions home to a cruel and diſgraceful Death. And ſo again, <hi>I am ready not to be bound only,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 21.13.</note> 
               <hi>but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to die at Jeruſalem for the name of the Lord Jeſus.</hi> For his Praiſe and Glory; ſo alſo ought we to be zealous toward it, if ever we hope to fulfil our Miniſtry.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Such ought to be loving and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected toward the Church, and People of God, to ſt a due Value upon their Souls, and to have an ardent good will toward them: Stewards ſhould have Love toward the Family, rejoyce in its welfare, delight in its Proſperity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without which they will either care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly neglect, or heedleſly and heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtly perform their Duty toward them. So muſt Miniſters be toward their Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and herein alſo follow that glorious Pattern St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſays concerning the <hi>Jews, I ſay the truth in Christ,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.1, 3.</note> 
               <hi>I lie not, my conſcience alſo bearing me wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the Holy Ghost, That I have
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:40316:25"/>great heavineſs and continual ſorrow in my heart: For I could wiſh myſelf were accurſed from Christ for my brethren, my kinſmen according to the fleſh.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.1.</note> 
               <hi>my hearts deſire and prayer to God for Iſrael is, that they might be ſaved.</hi> The ſame ardent Love and earning Bowels had he toward the <hi>Gentile</hi> Churches; ſo he tells the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians, Behold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.14, 15.</note> 
               <hi>the third time I am rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to come to you; and I will not be bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſom to you; for I ſeek not yours, but you: for children ought not to lay up for the parents, but the parents for the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. And I will very gladly ſpend and be ſpent for you, though the more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly I love you, the leſs I be loved.</hi> And ſo alſo he declares his Love to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 8, 11.</note> 
               <hi>But we were gentle among you, even as a nurſe cheriſheth her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: So, being affectionately deſirous of you, we were willing to have imparted to you, not the goſpel of God only, but alſo your own ſouls, becauſe ye were dear unto us. Ye know how we exhorted and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, and charged every one of you (as
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:40316:25"/>a father doth his children.)</hi> So ſhould our hearts be affected toward our Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſo we ſhould follow that Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, <hi>Feed the flock of God, and take the overſight thereof, not by conſtraint,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.2.</note> 
               <hi>but willingly; not for filthy lucre, but of a ready mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. Such muſt be humble and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent: Stewards muſt be of a compoſed and even Spirit, and not be in a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and ſtorm for every little Miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage; elſe they'll be unfit to manage the Affairs of a great Houſhold. So Miniſters muſt be of a ſetled and undi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed Spirit, not ſoon angry, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looking, paſſing by, and diſ-regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of, and not troubled at the ill Humors, and unhandſom and provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Carriage, which they muſt expect to meet with from ſome or other of the Family; yea, from them from whom they leaſt expect it, and leaſt deſerve it: This is expreſly command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them; a Biſhop muſt be patient:<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.3 4.</note> and ſo the Servant of the Lord muſt not ſtrive, but be gentle to all Men,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:40316:26"/>apt to teach,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 26.</note> patient, in meekneſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing thoſe that oppoſe themſelves, if God peradventure will give them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance to the acknowledging of the Truth, and that they may recover themſelves out of the Snare of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil's who are taken captive at his will They muſt imitate <hi>Moſes,</hi> and be zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in God's Cauſe; but meek and as unconcerned in their own, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Such muſt be blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and free from all Vice, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, praiſe worthy, and ſhining in all Graces and Vertues, in all Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity and venerable Deportment: Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards muſt be ſo, or they will never keep up their Authority in the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; if they be vain or vicious every one will deſpiſe them. So Miniſters muſt excel in all excellent and eminent Manners and Practice, and give all good Examples to their People; ſo they are enjoyn'd, <hi>Not as Lords over God's heritage,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>but as examples to the flock.</hi> So is <hi>Timothy</hi> charged, <hi>To be an example of the believers in word, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:40316:26"/>in charity, in ſpirit, in faith, in purity.</hi> And St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us that he was ſo, <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 20.</note> 
               <hi>be ye followers to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether of me; and marke them which walk ſo as ye have us for an enſample: For our converſation is in heaven, from whence alſo we look for the Saviour the Lord Jeſus Christ.</hi> Which they muſt do to confirm their Doctrine; they muſt preach out of the Pulpit by their Lives, as well as in the Pulpit by their Sermons: this they muſt do to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their Authority over, and their Reſpect from the Houſhold of God. So St. <hi>Paul</hi> directs <hi>Timothy</hi> to do, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving commanded him,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4 12.</note> 
               <hi>Let no man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe thy youth.</hi> He knew that ſome Perſons would be apt to diſdain to be taught, to be reproved by a young Lad, a beardleſs Boy, (as we uſe to ſay) &amp; ſo to contemn him; which he warns him againſt, and directs how he may avoid it, even by being an Enſample to the Believers in Word, in Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by ſhining in all Graces, Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Vertues toward God and Man.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:40316:27"/>And this was that which procured to <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt ſo great Reverence and Reſpect from <hi>Herod,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>He feared John, knowing that he was a just man and an holy, and obſerved him, and when he heard him, he did many things, and heard him gladly.</hi> So that his eminent Life and ſhining Converſation won him, from ſuch a cruel Tyrant, awe to his Perſon, attendance to his Doctrine, and obedience in many things to his Injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; tho' in the caſe of his <hi>Herodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as,</hi> rather than be parted from her, he would part <hi>John</hi>'s Head from his Body. The Title that the Holy Ghoſt gives Miniſters do all engage them hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; as they are called Embaſſadors, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Lights, Stars, Angels: How grave then, how ſhining, how exemplary, how heavenly ſhould they be? The chief Graces and Duries which they ought to have and perform, and the great Vices and Sins which they ought to ſubdue and avoid, we have ſpecified in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1, 7. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5, 6, 8. to which I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer you. In a word, let us but well
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:40316:27"/>ſtudy and follow the three Epiſtles of <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus;</hi> and we ſhall need no other Cannons or Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory; for he tells <hi>Timothy</hi> that 'twas for this end that he wrote thoſe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles to him, <hi>If I tarry long,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 15.</note> 
               <hi>that thou maist know how thou oughteſt to behave thyſelf in the houſe of God, which is the church of the living God, the pillar and ground of truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now becauſe I know that thro' the Corruptions of our own Nature, and our baſe inward Diſcouragements, and the manifold and great Oppoſitions and Contradictions that we do or may meet with. Motives are uſeful to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite us to all theſe Particulars, I ſhall take leave to hint ſome few very brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe a word to the wiſe is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Motives.</hi> 1. Becauſe of our Lord, whoſe Stewards we are, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in him, (as there may be in Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Lords and Maſters,) that can give us the leaſt Incouragement to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, to be remiſs in, or to contradict
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:40316:28"/>our Duty; but all to the contrary: God is not ignorant, but knows us, and all we do; he is not careleſs or heedleſs, but ſtrictly and exactly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves us, and all our Behaviours; he is not unconcerned about his Family, or no way touched with our Miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanors, and its Wrongs, but very jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of his own Glory, and his Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly's Good; he is not impotent or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to Avenge himſelf, or execute his Diſpleaſure, but Almighty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe of the Houſhold over which we are, 'tis the Church of God, his Flock and Heritage, his peculiar Treaſure, the Apple of his Eye, and the Darling of his Soul, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe of the great and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous things that are intruſted with us; Word, Ordinances, Diſcipline, Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, Heavenly and Divine Things, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerviated to God's greateſt Glory, and to Man's ſupream and eternal Good.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Becauſe of the great and glorious Reward, they ſhall receive that duely diſcharge their Stewardſhip: 'Tis ſaid
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:40316:28"/>concerning the good, wife, faithful and perſeveringly diligent Servant and Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Maith.</hi> 24 46, 47. <hi>i Luke</hi> 12. 43, 44. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 1 4.</note> that he is bleſſed; and his Lord will make him Ruler over all that he hath. And that the Elders who feed the Flock, and take the Overſight of it willingly, and of a ready Mind, and are Enſamples thereto: when the chief Shepherd ſhall appear,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.3</note> they ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a Crown of Glory that fadeth not away. Miniſters, good ones, ſhall ſhine like Stars, while others ſhall be but as the Firmament: We ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded not according to our Succeſs, but according to our Labour and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs in our Miniſtry; for Succeſs is God's, but Labour and Induſtry is ours by God's aſſiſtance, and therefore if there be a Miniſter more faithful, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious, zealous, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in his Function, tho' he convert no Souls, yet he ſhall receive a greater Reward then another, who is leſs ſo, and converts many Souls.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Becauſe of the dreadful Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which thoſe Stewards muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 21 48, 51.</note> which are nor, which do not, ſo
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:40316:29"/>as we have been exhorted to:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 12.45, 46.</note> In thoſe ſo frequently quoted Paſſages 'tis threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt the Lazy, the Secure, the Rude, and the Fighting Servant and Steward, <hi>That his Lord will come in a day that he looketh not for him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.16.</note> 
               <hi>and at an hour that he is not aware, and will cut him in ſunder; and will appoint him his portion with the hypocrites and the unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers.</hi> and Sr. <hi>Paul</hi> denounceth a Woe againſt himſelf if he preached not the Goſpel; and ſo to us, if we do not preach it and practice it as we ought. As good Miniſters are ordinarily the beſt Men, and do God moſt ſervice, and the Church moſt benefit on Earth; and ſo receive the greateſt degrees of Glory in Heaven: ſo bad and profane Miniſters are uſually the very worſt of Men, bring to God greateſt Diſhonour, to the Church greateſt Detriment, and ſhall lie down deepeſt in the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Pit.</p>
            <p n="6">6. I would add one more to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of our Perſwaſions, and that is, Becauſe in theſe days God hath given
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:40316:29"/>us ſo wonderfully our Liberty, hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened our Mouths, given us Freedom to preach, boldly and publickly to Congregations without fear of Fines or Bonds, and has hitherto to this day ſo graciouſly prolonged it to us, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us a Meeting of ſo many in Peace, Ingenuity and Gratitude ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain us to do all that poſſibly we can for God and his Glory, for Chriſt and his Church.</p>
            <p>We proceed to the ſecond Object of Exhortation:</p>
            <p n="2">2. This ſerves to exhort thoſe who intend for the Miniſtry, to conſider well and wiſely what they are about, what the greatneſs, the weight, the charge of this Stewardſhip are, and what they ought to be and do that are of this Function, and ſo not to dare to enter raſhly thereon, without the due Qualifications (at leaſt in ſome good meaſure,) of Head, Heart, and Life, of Learning and Orthodoxy, of Grace and Experience, of Manners and Praiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſs, of Converſation. St. <hi>Paul</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:40316:30"/>enjoyns that a Miniſter muſt not be <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6.</note> a Novice, or a Novel Graft juſt now grafted in; he muſt not be a Novice in the Faith, nor a Novice in Grace, nor a Novice in Manners. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons muſt not take the Charge of the Myſteries of God to themſelves, when they are but little better qualified then the meaneſt Servants, not ſo well as moſt, yea, perhaps really not of the Family of God themſelves, of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible Church by Grace. I would not here be thought to diſcourage all young Men from entring upon the Miniſtry, (eſpecially now that the <hi>Church of God</hi> is in ſo great need of Paſtors,) for I well know that a young <hi>Timothy</hi> may be as well qualified for it, and demean himſelf as well in it, as a more aged <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollos:</hi> But then I am ſure ſuch quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied young Men will be the leaſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and the moſt backward to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take it, becauſe they know the Naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs of their own Hearts, the ſtrength and working of their own Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; they know they have a hard task
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:40316:30"/>to look after, and to keep their own Souls, and therefore they tremble to take upon them the Charge of others Souls; to be put upon keeping others Vine-yards, when they cannot keep their own; and ſo muſt be thruſt out (as it were) with Violence into the Lord's Harveſt. Whereas they who are leaſt prepared and moſt unfit, are the moſt forward to undertake the Miniſtry, and will not be reſtrained by any Cautions from ruſhing upon that Function, for which they have no Fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs nor Preparation.</p>
            <p>I proceed to the third Object of this Uſe:</p>
            <p n="3">3. This ſerves to exhort the Family and Houſhold over which Miniſters are Stewards; that in the words of the Text, <hi>They would ſo account of them,</hi> duly carry it toward them in Mind, Heart, and Practice; I ſhall mention a few Particulars very briefly:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Do you Honour and Reverence your Miniſters as in ſuch a Function; for tho' they be your Fellow-ſervants
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:40316:31"/>toward God, yet they are your Superiors in the Family, having the higheſt Office therein, and none above them as they are Stewards of God's Myſteries, (for tho' we acknowledge the Magiſtrate to have an Authority about ſacred Things and Perſons, yet he has nothing to do in them,) and ſo are ſaid in Scripture,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.12.</note> to be over you, to have the Rule over you; and in thoſe fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Texts, the Lord Chriſt is ſaid to make his Servants and his Stewards Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers over all his Houſhold:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.27.</note> and that which the Apoſtle calls Diſpenſation or Steward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in one Verſe,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.17, 18.</note> in the very next he calls Power or Authority. Wherefore you owe them Reſpect and Reverence, which you muſt have in your Hearts and Carriage toward their Perſons.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Obey your Miniſters, and ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting yourſelves unto them, to their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in Chriſt you muſt ſubmit, and to their Commands from Chriſt you muſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey: (If what we enjoyn be not accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Word, do not obey us; as if what we teach be not according to it, do not believe us; and if what we threaten be not according to it, do not fear it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) Whatever we enjoyn or forbid, if it be proved from the Word of Chriſt, you muſt do the one and forbear the other: You
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:40316:31"/>are commanded,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17.</note> To <hi>obey them that have the rule over you, and ſubmit yourſelves; for they watch for your ſouls, as they that must, give account, that they may do it with joy and not with grief, for that is unprofitable for you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Love your Miniſters dearly, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect them highly, (in all theſe particulars we ſuppoſe them to be ſuch as deſerve the name of Miniſters, and do their Duty) for their great Labours, and the great and ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimable Profit they bring (if the Fault be not your own,) to your own Souls: So they loved St. <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 20.36, 38.</note> who when he took his Leave of them, and told them he ſhould ſee them no more; wept ſore, and fell on his neck and kiſſed him. And yet more the <hi>Galatians</hi> loved him at their firſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, and before they were alienated from him by Underminers and falſe Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, for he bears them Record,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>That if it had been poſſible they would have plucked out their eyes, and have given them to him;</hi> (that is) if thereby they could have done him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſervice) And the Apoſtle commands you all to eſteem them very highly in love for their Works ſake, <hi>Who labour among you, and are over you in the Lord, and admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Content yourſelves with the Portion of God's Myſteries which they diſtribute
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:40316:32"/>to you: You muſt conclude that ſuch are wiſer then you, and better know what is beſt for your Souls than yourſelves; if they reprove you, if they caution you, look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it as more proper and uſeful then Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation and Encouragement: If they adviſe you to abſtain a ſhort time longer from the Sacrament, till you have gotten more Knowledge and better Preparation; not to exclude you from it, but that you may come more profitably and comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to it, be well content, and do not fling off in a Pet, as the fooliſh and inexcuſable manner of ſome is, and never come near and hear him more.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Help your Miniſters in their Charge and Labour, and make it as eaſie as you can for them: The <hi>Stewardſhip and Charge of God's Myſteries, and of Souls,</hi> is a moſt weighty and tremendous Burden, which you ſhould endeavour to alleviate, which you ſhould do, by being thriving Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in Knowledge and Godlineſs, for this would be their Delight, and where the Heart is joyful, there the Labour will be eaſie. By edubating your Families (Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and Maſters) in the Faith of Chriſt, and the Fear of God; by watching loving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and prudently one over another, and mutually reproving, adviſing, exhorting,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:40316:32"/>warning, as juſt cauſe is given. Were theſe things duly performed by the People, much of the Miniſter's Care and Pain would be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh'd.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Pray to God fervently for ſuch Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards when you are deſtitute of them; and bleſs God enlargedly for them when you are furniſh'd with them, as one of the greateſt Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings under Heaven. Thus we have finiſh'd the Uſe of Exhortation, and proceed to a third.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This Doctrin ſerves by way of Reproof, 1. To Stewards. 2. To the Houſhold.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Repreh.</hi> 1. Of all Miniſters that either are unable or unwilling to do the Duty of the Stewards of God's Houſe, that either neglect or contradict their Duty either in Language or Carriage, who by ſpeaking or living do poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or diſorder the Houſhold, or by ſilence and lazineſs ſtarve it, the condition of ſuch Wretches is miſerable and dreadful.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Of thoſe of the Houſhold who either o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit or contradict theſe Duties they owe to their Miniſters, do not ſo account of them as of god's Stewards, but demeans themſelves quite contrary; theſe little conſider that the Diſ-reſpects and Injuries they offer the Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards (the Miniſters) are offered to the Lord (even God himſelf) of the Houſhold; yet he tells them they are ſo, <hi>He that deſpiſeth you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth me, and he that deſpiſeth me deſpiſeth him
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:40316:33"/>that ſent me,</hi> Luke 10.16. And Chriſt's and God's Diſhonour will redound to your De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, if Repentance and Reformaton prevent not. I proceed to the fourth and laſt Uſe.</p>
            <p>This Doctrine alſo ſerves for Comfort to laborious Miniſters and People.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſol.</hi> 1. To all good, able, faithful, ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Miniſters, who faithfully diſcharge, and duly demean themſelves in their Stewardſhip; 2uch are moſt excellent and moſt bleſſed ones, whatever a proud, fooliſh and profane World judges of them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To all thoſe of the Family that duely demean themſelves toward their Miniſters, and in all things do dutifully account of them as Miniſters of Chriſt, and Stewards of the Myſteries of God, for the Honour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, the Obedience and Duty that are given to theſe are given to the Lord Chriſt himſelf, as he himſelf aſſures us, <hi>He that heareth you, heareth me, and the honours that is given to Christ ſhall return an hundred fold into the boſom of him, that gives it,</hi> Luke 10.16. Would to God that all Congregations had ſuch Stewards and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, and that all Stewards had ſuch a Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Congregation, each diſcharging theſe Duties here diſcourſed of; for ſo 'twould fare very well with the Church of God.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:40316:33"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
